<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The speech or declaration of John Pym, Esq. &amp;c.</title>
            <author>Pym, John, 1584-1643.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56351</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P4294</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R479151</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14513528</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14513528</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102465</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56351)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102465)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1067:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The speech or declaration of John Pym, Esq. &amp;c.</title>
                  <author>Pym, John, 1584-1643.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages stained and with print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1625-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb facs="tcp:102465:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:102465:1"/>
            <head>THE SPEECH OR DECLARATION OF <hi>JOHN PYM,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORDS,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Any dayes have beene ſpent in maintenance of the Impeachment of the Earle of Strafford, by the Houſe of Commons, whereby he ſtands charged with High Treaſon: And your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips have heard his Defence with Patience and with as much favour as Iuſtice would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low: We have paſſed through our Evidence, and the Reſult of all this is, that it remaines clearly proved, That the Earle of Strafford hath indeavoured by his words, actions, and counſells, to ſubvert the Fundamentall Lawes of England and Ireland, and to introduce an Arbitrary, and Tyrannicall Government.</p>
            <p>This is the envenomed Arrow for which he inquired in the beginning of his Replication this day, which hath infected all his Blood: This is that Intoxicating Cup, (to uſe his owne Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phor) which hath tainted his Iudgement, and poiſoned his Heart:
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:102465:2"/> From hence was infuſed that Specificall Difference which tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his Speeches, his Actions, his Counſels into Treaſon; Not Cumulative, as he expreſt it, as if many Miſdemeanours could make one, Treaſon; but Formally and Eſſentially. It is the End that doth enforme Actions, and doth ſpecificate the nature of them, making not onely criminall, but even indifferent words and actions to be Treaſon, being done and ſpoken with a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable intention.</p>
            <p>That which is given to mee in charge is to ſhew the quality of the offence, how hainous it is in the nature, how miſchievous in the effect of it; which will beſt appeare if it be examined by that Law, to which he himſelfe appealed, that univerſall, that ſupreame Law, Salus populi: This is the Element of all Lawes, out of which they are derived; the End of all Laws, to which they are deſigned, and in which they, are perfected. How farre it ſtands in oppoſition to this Law, I ſhall endevour to ſhew in ſome Conſiderations which I ſhall preſent to your Lordſhips, all ariſing out of the Evidence which hath beene opened.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt is this: It is an offence comprehending all other offences; here you ſhall finde ſeverall Treaſons, Murthers, Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines, Oppreſſions, Perjuries.</p>
            <p>The Earth hath a Seminary vertue, whereby it doth produce all Herbs and Plants, and other Vegetables: There is in this Crime, a Seminary of all Evills hurtfull to a State; and if you conſider the Reaſons of it, it muſt needs be ſo: The Law is that which puts a difference betwixt good and evill, betwixt juſt and unjuſt; If you take away the Law, all things will fall into a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, every man will become a Law to himſelfe, which in the depraved condition of humane nature, muſt needs produce ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great enormities: Luſt will become a Law, and Envy will become a Law, Covetouſneſſe and Ambition will become Lawes; and what dictates, what deciſions ſuch Lawes will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce, may eaſily be diſcerned in the late Government of Ireland: The Law hath a power to prevent, to reſtraine, to repaire evills; without this, all kind of miſchiefes and diſtempers will breake in upon a State.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:102465:2"/>It is the Law that doth intitle the King to the Allegeance and ſervice of his people, it intitles the people to the protection and juſtice of the King. It is God alone who ſubſiſts by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, all other things ſubſiſt in a mutuall dependence and rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Hee was a wiſe man that ſaid, that the King ſubſiſted by the field that is tilled: It is the labour of the people that ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports the Crowne: If you take away the protection of the King, the vigour and cheerefulneſſe of Alleg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> will be taken away though the Obligation remaine.</p>
            <p>The Law is the Boundary, the Meaſure betwixt the Kings Prerogative, and the peoples Liberty: Whiles theſe move in their owne Orbe, they are a ſupport and ſecurity to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; The Prerogative a cover and defence to the Liberty of the people, and the people by their Liberty are enabled to be a foundation to the Prerogative; but if theſe bounds be ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, that they enter into conteſtation and conflict, one of theſe miſchiefes muſt needs enſue: If the Prerogative of the King overwhelme the Liberty of the people, it will be turned into Tyranny; if Liberty undermine the Prerogative, it will grow into Anarchy,</p>
            <p>The Law is the ſafegard, the cuſtody of all private intereſt: Your Honours, your Lives, your Liberties and eſtates are all in the keeping of the Law; without this every man hath a like right to any thing, and this is the condition into which the Iriſh were brought by the Earle of Strafford: And the reaſon which hee gave for it, hath more miſchiefe in it than the thing it ſelfe, They were a Conquered Nation. There cannot be a word more pregnant &amp; fruitfull in Treaſon, than that word is: There are few Nations in the world that have not bin conquered; and no doubt but the Conqueror may give what Lawes he pleaſe to thoſe that are conquered: But if the ſucceeding Pacts and Agreements doe not limit and reſtraine that right, what people can be ſecure? England hath been conquered, and Wales hath been conquered, and by this reaſon will be in little better caſe than Ireland. If the King by the Right of a Conqueror gives Laws to his people, ſhall not the people by the ſame reaſon be reſtored to the right of the conquered, to recover their liberty if they can? What can be more hurtfull, more pernitious to both, then ſuch propoſitions at theſe?
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:102465:3"/> And in theſe particulars is determined the firſt Conſideration.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond Conſideration is this: This Arbitrary power is dangerous to the Kings Perſon, and dangerous to his Crowne: It is apt to cheriſh ambition, uſurpation, and oppreſſion in great men, and to beget ſedition and diſcontent in the People; and both theſe have been, and in reaſon muſt ever be cauſes of great trouble and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>teration to Princes and States.</p>
            <p>If the Hiſtories of thoſe Eaſterne Countries be peruſed, where Princes order their affaires according to the miſchievous prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of the E. of Strafford, looſe and abſolved from all Rules of Government, they will be found to be frequent in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtions, full of Maſſacres, and of the tragicall ends of Princes. If any man ſhall looke into our owne Stories, in the times when the Lawes were moſt neglected, he ſhall find them full of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions, of Civill diſtempers; whereby the Kings that then reigned, were alwayes kept in want and diſtreſſe; the people conſumed with Civill warres: and by ſuch wicked Counſells as theſe, ſome of our Princes have beene brought to ſuch miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ends, as no honeſt heart can remember without horrour, and earneſt Prayer, that it may never be ſo againe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third Conſideration is this, The ſubverſion of the Lawes; And this arbitrary power, as it is dangerous to the Kings Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and to his Crowne, ſo is it in other reſpects very prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall to his Majeſty in his Honour, Profit, and greatneſſe; and yet theſe are the gildings and paintings that are put upon ſuch Counſels; Theſe are for your Honour, for your Service; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as in truth they are contrary to both: But if I ſhall take off this varniſh, I hope they ſhall then appeare in their owne native deformity, and therefore I deſire to conſider them by theſe Rules.</p>
            <p>It cannot be for the honour of a King, that his ſacred au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority ſhould be uſed in the practiſe of in juſtice &amp; oppreſſion; that his Name ſhould be applyed to patronize ſuch horrid crimes, as have beene repreſented in Evidence againſt the Earle of Strafford; and yet how frequently, how preſumptuouſly his Commands, his Letters have beene vouched throughout the courſe of this Defence, your Lordſhips have heard. When the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:102465:3"/> Iudges doe juſtice, it is the Kings Iuſtice, and this is for his ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nour, becauſe he is the Fountaine of Iuſtice: but when they doe injuſtice, the offence is their owne: But thoſe Officers and Miniſters of the King, who are moſt officious in the exerciſe of this Arbitrary power, they doe it commonly for their advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage; and when they are queſtioned for it, then they fly to the Kings intereſt, to his direction: And truly my Lords, this is a very unequall diſtribution for the King, that the diſhonour of evill courſes ſhould be caſt upon him, and they to have the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage.</p>
            <p>The prejudice which it brings to him in regard of his profit, is no leſſe apparant: It deprives him of the moſt beneficiall, and moſt certaine Revenue of his Crowne, that is, the voluntary aids and ſupplies of his people; his other Revenues, conſiſting of goodly Demeanes, and great Manors, have by Grants beene alienated from the Crowne, and are now exceedingly dimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and impaired: But this Revenue it cannot be ſold, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be burdened with any Penſions or Annuities, but comes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely to the Crowne. It is now almoſt fifteene yeeres ſince his Majeſty had any aſſiſtance from his people; and theſe illegall wayes of ſupplying the King were never preſt with more vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and art, then they have beene in this time; and yet I may upon very good grounds affirme, that in the laſt fifteene yeeres of Queene Elizabeth, ſhe received more by the Bounty and Affection of her Subjects, then hath come to His Majeſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es Cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers by all the inordinate and rigorous courſes which have been taken. And as thoſe Supplies were more beneficiall in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt of them, ſo were they like in the uſe and imployment of them.</p>
            <p>Another way of prejudice to his Majeſties profit, is this: Such Arbitrary courſes exhauſt the people, and diſable them, when there ſhall be occaſion, to give ſuch plentifull ſupplyes, as otherwiſe they would doe. I ſhall need no other proofe of this, then the Iriſh Government under my L. of Strafford, where the wealth of the kingdome is ſo conſumed by thoſe horrible exacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and burdens, that it is thought the Subſidies lately granted will amount to little more then halfe the proportion of the laſt Subſidies. The two former wayes are hurtfull to the Kings pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:102465:4"/> in that reſpect which they call Luceum-Ceſſans, by dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing his receipts; But there is a third, fuller of miſchiefe, and it is in that reſpect which they call Damnum emergens, by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing his disburſements: Such irregular and exhorbitant attempts upon the Liberties of the people, are apt to produce ſuch miſerable diſtractions and diſtempers, as will put the King and kingdomes to ſuch vaſt expences and loſſes in a ſhort time, as will not be recovered in many yeeres: Wee need not goe farre to ſeeke a proofe of this, theſe two laſt yeares will be a ſufficient evidence, within which time I aſſure my ſelfe, it may be proved, that more Treaſure hath beene waſted, more loſſe ſuſtained by his Majeſty and his Subjects, then was ſpent by Queene Elizabeth in all the War of Tyrone, and in thoſe many brave Attempts againſt the King of Spaine, and the royall aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance which ſhe gave to France, and the Low-Countries, during all her Reigne.</p>
            <p>As for Greatneſſe, this Arbitrary power is apt to hinder and impaire it, not onely at home, but abroad. A kingdome is a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of men conjoyned under one Government, for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good: The World is a ſociety of kindomes and States. The Kings greatneſſe conſiſts not onely in his Dominion over his Subjects at home, but in the influence which hee hath upon States abroad, That he ſhould bee great even among Kings, and by his wiſedome and authority ſo to incline and diſpoſe the affaires of o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her States and Nations, and thoſe great events which fall out in the World, as ſhall be for the good of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, and for the peculiar advantage of his owne people. This is the moſt glorious, and magnificent greatneſſe, to be able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve diſtreſſed Princes, to ſupport his owne friends and Allies, to prevent the ambitious deſignes of other Kings; and how much this Kingdome hath beene impaired in this kinde, by the late miſchievous counſels your Lordſhips beſt know, who at a neere diſtance, and with a more cleare ſight, doe appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend theſe publique and great affaires, then I can doe. Yet this much I dare boldly ſay, that if his Majeſtie had not with great wiſedome and goodneſſe forſaken that way wherein the Earle of Strafford had put him, we ſhould within a ſhort time have beene brought into that miſerable condition, as to have beene vſeleſſe to our friends, contemptible to our enemies,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:102465:4"/> and uncapable of undertaking any great Deſigne either at home or abroad.</p>
            <p>A fourth Conſideration is, That this Arbitrary and Tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Power, which the Earle of Strafford did exerciſe in his owne perſon, and to which he did adviſe his Majeſty, is inconſiſtent with the Peace; the Wealth, the Proſperity of a Nation; It is deſtructive to Iuſtice, the Mother of Peace; to Induſtry, the ſpring of Wealth; to Valour, which is the active vertue where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the proſperity of a Nation can onely be procured, confirmed and inlarged.</p>
            <p>It is not onely apt to take away Peace, and ſo intangle the Nation with Warres, but doth corrupt Peace, and puts ſuch a malignity into it, as produceth the Effects of warre. We need ſeeke no other proofe of this, but the Earle of Straffords Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, where the Iriſh, both Nobility and others, had as little ſecurity of their Perſons or Eſtates in this peaceable time, as if the Kingdome had beene under the rage and fury of warre.</p>
            <p>And as for Induſtry and Valour, who will take paines for that, which when hee hath gotten, is not his owne? Or who fight for that wherein he hath no other intereſt, but ſuch as is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the will of another? The Ancient encouragement to men that were to defend their Countries was this, That they were to hazard their Perſon, pro Aris &amp; Focis, for their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and for their Houſes; But by this Arbitrary way which was practiſed in Ireland, and counſelled here, no man had any certainty, either of Religion, or of his Houſe, or any thing elſe to be his owne; But beſides this, ſuch Arbitrary cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes have an ill operation upon the courage of a Nation, by embaſing the hearts of the people: A ſervile condition doth for the moſt part beget in men a ſlaviſh temper and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition. Thoſe that live ſo much under the Whip and the Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lory, and ſuch ſervile Engines, as were frequently uſed by the Earle of Strafford, they may have the dregs of valor, ſullenneſſe, and ſtubbornneſſe, which may make them prone to Mutinies, and diſcontents; but thoſe Noble and gallant affections, which put men on brave Deſignes and Attempts for the preſervation or inlargement of a Kingdome, they are hardly capable of. Shall it be Treaſon to embaſe the Kings Coyne, though but a piece
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:102465:5"/> of twelve-pence, or ſix-pence, and muſt it not needs be the effect of a greater Treaſon, to embaſe the ſpirits of his Subjects, and to ſet a ſtamp and Character of ſervitude upon them, whereby they ſhall be diſabled to doe any thing for the ſervice of the King or Common-wealth?</p>
            <p>The fifth Conſideration is this, That the exerciſe of this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>trary Government, in times of ſudden danger, by the inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of an enemy, will diſable his Majeſty to preſerve himſelfe and his Subjects from that danger. This is the only pretence by which the Earle of Strafford, and ſuch other miſchievous Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours would induce his Majeſty to make uſe of it; and if it be unfit for ſuch an occaſion, I know nothing that can be alledged in maintenance of it.</p>
            <p>When warre threatens a Kingdome by the comming of a forraine Enemy, it is no time then to diſcontent the people, to make them weary of the preſent Government and more incline<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to a Change; The ſupplies which are to come in this way, will be unready, uncertain; there can be no aſſurance of them, no dependence upon them, either for time or proportion: And if ſome money be gotten in ſuch a way, the Diſtractions, Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Diſtempers, which this courſe is apt to produce, will be more prejudiciall to the publique ſafety, than the ſupply can advantagious to it; and of this we have had ſufficient experience the laſt Summer.</p>
            <p>The ſixt, That this crime of ſubverting the Lawes, and intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing an Arbitrary and Tyrannicall Government, is contrary to to the Pact and Covenant betwixt the King and his people. That which was ſpoken of before, was the legall union of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance and Protection; this is a perſonall union by mutuall agreement and ſtipulation, confirmed by oath on both ſides: The King and his people are obliged to one another in the neereſt relations; He is a Father, and a childe is called in Law, Pars Patris: He is the Husband of the Common-wealth, they have the ſame intereſts, they are inſeparable in their condition, be it good or evill; He is the Head, they are the Body; there is ſuch an incorporation as cannot be diſſolved without the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of both.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:102465:5"/>When Iuſtice Thorpe, in Edward the thirds time, was by the Parliament condemned to death for Bribery, the reaſon of that judgement is given, becauſe he had broken the Kings Oath, not that he had broken his owne oath, but that hee had broken the Kings oath, that ſolemne and great obligation, which is the ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the whole Kingdome: If for a Iudge to take a ſmall ſumme in a private cauſe, was adjudged Capitall, how much greater was this offence, whereby the Earle of Strafford hath broken the Kings Oath in the whole courſe of his government in Ireland, to the prejudice of ſo many of his Majeſties Subjects, in their Lives, Liberties, and Eſtates, and to the danger of all the reſt?</p>
            <p>The Doctrine of the Papiſts, Fides non eſt ſervanda cum Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticis, is an abominable Doctrine; yet that other Tenet more peculiar to the Ieſuits is more pernicious, whereby Subjects are diſcharged from their oath of Allegeance to their Prince when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever the Pope pleaſeth; This may be added to make the third no leſſe miſchievous and deſtructive to humane ſociety, then either of the reſt; That the King is not bound by that oath which he hath taken to obſerve the Lawes of the Kingdome, but may when he ſees cauſe, lay Taxes and Burthens upon them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their conſent, contrary to the Lawes and Liberties of the Kingdome. This hath beene preached and publiſhed by divers; And this is that which hath beene practiſed in Ireland by the Earle of Strafford, in his government there, and endevoured to be brought into England, by his Counſell here.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> The ſeventh is this; It is an offence that is contrary to the end of Government; The end of Government was to prevent op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions; to limit and reſtraine the exceſſive power and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of great men, to open the paſſages of Iuſtice with indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency towards all; This Arbitrary power is apt to induce and incourage all kinde of inſolencies.</p>
            <p>Another end of Government, is to preſerve men in their Eſtates, to ſecure them in their Lives and Liberties; but if this Deſigne had taken effect, and could have beene ſetled in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, as it was practiſed in Ireland, no man would have had more certainty in his owne, then power would have allowed him: but theſe two have been ſpoken of before, there are two behind more important, which have not yet beene touched.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:102465:6"/>It is the end of Governement, that vertue ſhould be cheriſht, vice ſuppreſt; but where this Arbitrary and unlimited power is ſet up, a way is open not onely for the ſecurity, but for the advancement and incouragement of evill; Such men as are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt for the execution and maintenance of this Power, are onely capable of preferment; and others who will not be inſtruments of any unjuſt commands, who make a conſcience to doe nothing againſt the Lawes of the Kingdome, and liberties of the Subject, are not onely not paſſable for imployment, but ſubject to much jealouſie and danger.</p>
            <p>It is the end of Government, that all accidents and events, all Counſells and Deſignes ſhould be improved to the publique good: But this Arbitrarie Power is apt to diſpoſe all to the maintenance of it ſelfe. The wiſdome of the Counſell Table, the Authority of the Courts of Iuſtice, the induſtry of all the Officers of the Crowne have beene moſt carefully exerciſed in this; the Learning of our Divines, the Iuriſdiction of our Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops have beene moulded and diſpoſed to the ſame effect, which though it were begun before the E. of Straffords Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yet it hath beene exceedingly furthered and advanced by him.</p>
            <p>Vnder this colour and pretence of maintaining the Kings Power and Prerogative many dangerous practiſes againſt the peace and ſafetie of this kingdome have beene undertaken and promoted. The increaſe of Popery, and the favours and incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of Papiſts have beene, and ſtill are a great grievance and danger to the Kingdome: The innovations in matters of Religion, the uſurpations of the Clergie, the manifold burdens and taxations upon the people, have beene a great cauſe of our preſent diſtempers and diſorders; and yet thoſe who have beene chiefe Furtherers and Actors of ſuch Miſchiefes, have had their Credit and Authority from this, That they were forward to maintaine this Power. The E. of Strafford had the firſt riſe of his greatneſſe from this, and in his Apologie and Defence, as your Lordſhips have heard, this hath had a maine part.</p>
            <p>The Royall Power, and Majeſtie of Kings, is moſt glorious in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:102465:6"/> the proſperitie and happineſſe of the people; the perfection of all things conſiſts in the end for which they were ordained, God onely is his owne end, all other things have a further end beyond themſelves, in attaining whereof their owne happineſſe conſiſts: If the meanes and the end be ſet in oppoſition to one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, it muſt needs cauſe an impotency and defect of both.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> The eight Conſideration is, The vanitie and abſurdity of thoſe excuſes and juſtifications which he made for himſelfe, whereof divers particulars have been mentioned in the courſe of his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That he is a Counſellor, and might not be queſtioned for any thing which he adviſed according to his conſcience; The ground is true, there is a liberty belongs to Counſellors, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing corrupts Counſels more then Fear; Hee that will have the priviledge of a Counſellor, muſt keepe within the iuſt bounds of a Counſellor; thoſe matters are the proper ſubiects of Counſell, which in their times and occaſions, may be good or beneficiall to the King or Common-wealth; But ſuch treaſons as theſe, the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of the Lawes, violation of Liberties, they can never be good, or iuſtifiable by any circumſtance, or occaſion; and therefore his being a Counſellor, makes his fault much more hainous, as being committed againſt a greater Truſt, and in a way of much miſchiefe and danger, leſt his Maieſties conſcience and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (upon which the whole courſe and frame of his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment doe much depend) ſhould be poyſoned and infected with ſuch wicked principles and deſignes: And this hee hath endeavoured to doe, which by all Lawes, and in all times hath in this Kingdome beene reckoned a Crime of an High Nature.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Hee labours to intereſt your Lordſhips in his cauſe, by al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging, It may be dangerous to your ſelves, and your Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, who by your birth are fitteſt to be neare his Maieſty, in places of truſt and Authority, if you ſhould be ſubiect to be queſtioned for matters delivered in Counſell. To this was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that it was hoped their Lordſhips would rather La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to ſecure themſelves, and their poſteritie, in the exerciſe of their vertues, then of their vices, that ſo they might together
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:102465:7"/> with their owne honour and greatneſſe, preſerve the honour and greatneſſe, both of the King and kingdome.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Another excuſe was this, that whatſoever he hath ſpoken was out of a good intention; Sometimes good and evill, truth and falſhood lie ſo neare together, that they are hardly to be diſtinguiſhed: Matters hurtfull and dangerous may be accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with ſuch circumſtances as may make it appeare uſefull and convenient, and in all ſuch caſes, good intention will juſtifie e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill Counſell; But where the matters propounded are evill in their owne nature, ſuch as the matters are wherewith the Earle of Strafford is charged, to breake a publique faith, to ſubvert Laws and Government, they can never be juſtified by any intentions, how ſpeeches, or good ſoever they be pretended.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Hee alledgeth it was a time of great neceſſitie and danger, when ſuch counſels were neceſſarie for preſervation of the State. Neceſſitie hath beene ſpoken of before, as it relates to the Cauſe; now it is conſidered as it relates to the Perſon; if there were any neceſſitie, it was of his owne making; he by his evill counſell had brought the King into a neceſſitie, and by no Rules of Iuſtice, can be allowed to gaine this advantage by his owne fault, as to make that a ground of his juſtification, which is a great part of his offence.</p>
            <p n="5">5. He hath often inſinuated this, That it was for his Majeſties ſervice in maintenance of that Soveraigne Power with which he is intruſted by God for the good of his people. The Anſwer is this, No doubt but that Soveraigne Power wherewith his Majeſtie is intruſted for the publique good, hath many glorious effects, the better to inable him thereunto; But without doubt this is none of them, That by his owne will he may lay any Taxe or Impoſition upon his people without their conſent in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. This hath now been five times adjudged by both Houſes: In the Caſe of the Loanes, In condemning the Commiſſion of Exciſe, In the Reſolution upon the Saving offered to be added to the Petition of Right, In the ſentence againſt Manwaring, and now lately, In condemning the Shipmoney; And if the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne power of the King can produce no ſuch effect as this, the Allegation of it is an Aggravation, and no Diminution of his
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:102465:7"/> offence, becauſe thereby he doth labour to intereſt the King a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the juſt grievance and complaint of the People.</p>
            <p n="6">6. This Counſell was propounded with divers limitations, and Proviſions; for ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ing and repairing the libertie of the people. This implies a contradiction to maintaine an Arbitrary and abſolute Power, and yet to reſtraine it with limitations, and proviſions, for even thoſe limitations and proviſions will be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the ſame abſolute Power, and to be diſpenſed in ſuch manner, and at ſuch time, as it ſelfe ſhall determine; let the grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances and oppreſſions be never ſo heavy, the Subject is left with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all remedie, but at his Majeſties owne pleaſure.</p>
            <p n="7">7 He alledgeth, they were but words, and no effect followed. This needs no anſwer, but that the miſerable diſtempers into which he hath brought all the three Kingdomes, will be evidence ſufficient that his wicked Counſels have had ſuch miſchievous effects within theſe two or three laſt yeeres, that many yeeres peace will hardly repaire thoſe loſſes, and other great miſchiefes which the Common-wealth hath ſuſtained.</p>
            <p>Theſe excuſes have been collected out of the ſeverall parts of his Defence; perchance ſome others are omitted, which I doubt not have beene anſwered by ſome of my Collegues, and are of no importance, either to perplex or to hinder your Lordſhips judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, touching the hainouſneſſe of this Crime.</p>
            <p>The ninth Conſideration is this, That if this be Treaſon, in the nature of it, it doth exceed all other Treaſons in this, that in the Deſigne, and endeavour of the Author, it was to be a conſtant &amp; permanent Treaſon; other Treaſons tranſient, as being confined within thoſe particular Actions and Proportions wherein they did conſiſt, and thoſe being paſt, the Treaſon ceaſeth.</p>
            <p>The Powder-treaſon was full of horror and malignity, yet it is paſt many yeeres ſince; The murder of that Magnanimous and glorious King, Henry the fourth of France, was a great and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid Treaſon; And ſo were thoſe manifold attempts againſt Qu. Elizabeth of bleſſed memory; but they are long ſince paſt, the Deteſtation of them onely remaines in Hiſtories, and in the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:102465:8"/> minds of men; and will ever remaine; But this Treaſon, if it had taken effect, was to be a ſtanding, perpetuall Treaſon, which would have beene in continuall act, not determined within one time or age, but tranſmitted to Poſterity, even from one gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to another.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> The tenth conſideration is this, That as it is a Crime odious in the nature of it, ſo it is odious in the judgement and eſtimation of the Law; to alter the ſetled frame and conſtitution of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is Treaſon in any eſtate; The Lawes whereby all other parts of a Kingdome are preſerved, ſhould be very vaine and defective, if they had not a power to ſecure and preſerve themſelves.</p>
            <p>The forfeitures inflicted for Treaſon by our Law, are of Life, Honor, and Eſtate, even all that can be forfeited, and this Priſoner having committed ſo many Treaſons, although he ſhould pay all theſe forfeitures, will be ſtill a Debtor to the Common-wealth: Nothing can be more equall, then that hee ſhould periſh by the Iuſtice of that Law which hee would have ſubverted; Neither will this be a new way of blood; There are markes enough to trace this Law to the very originall of this Kingdome: And if it hath not beene put in execution, as he allegeth, this 240. yeers, it was not for want of Law, but that all that time hath not bred a man bold enough to commit ſuch Crimes as theſe; which is a circumſtance much aggravating his offence, and making him no whit leſſe liable to puniſhment, becauſe he is the onely man that in ſo long a time hath ventured upon ſuch a Treaſon as this.</p>
            <p>It belongs to the charge of another to make it appeare to your Lordſhips, that the Crimes and offences proved againſt the Earle of Strafford, are High Treaſon by the Lawes and Statutes of this Realme, whoſe learning and other abilities are much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for that ſervice. But for the time and manner of performing this, we are to reſort to the Direction of the houſe of Commons, having in this which is already done, diſpatched all thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions which we have received; and concerning further pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, for clearing all Queſtions and Objections in Law, your Lordſhips will heare from the Houſe of Commons in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient time.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:102465:8"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
